PAUL JAY: Welcome back to Reality Asserts
Itself on The Real News Network.
We're continuing our series of interviews
with John Kiriakou, the former CIA officer
who spent 23 months in jail and, as we record
the interview, has got about 36, 37 days left
[incompr.] house arrest, because--well, really
because he went on television and said that
torture was official U.S. policy. He was charged
with giving a reporter the name of a CIA officer,
who the reporter actually never published,
and, as far as I understand it, the name was
out there anyway, but they wanted to get them.
And we'll get into that story more in detail
further into this series. But now we're going
to carry on.
We have in the last episode talked a lot about
the Iraq War. About a year before the Iraq
War, more or less, John is posted to Pakistan.
And thanks for joining us.
JOHN C. KIRIAKOU: Good to be here.
JAY: Now, anyone that knows the situation
in Afghanistan knows that--and I don't think
anybody disputes that the Pakistan army intelligence,
the ISI, to a large extent with some Saudi
cooperation and money, helped nurture and
create the Taliban.
KIRIAKOU: Yes. Pakistani intelligence services
created the Taliban with Saudi money.
JAY: With Saudi money.
KIRIAKOU: Mhm.
JAY: And start to spread Wahhabism, which
is not the religious cultural traditions of
Afghanistan. The Taliban and all the links
with al-Qaeda and Osama bin Laden, clearly
the Pakistani intelligence are not only fully
aware that the Taliban works in collaboration
with the Pakistani ISI. So the Osama bin Laden
in Afghanistan is done in some ways under
the auspices of the Pakistani intelligence
service.
KIRIAKOU: I always believed that.
JAY: And I was told that in Kandahar, and
there seemed to be no disputing it.
So you go to Pakistan in 2002. You're the
counterterrorism chief CIA official in Pakistan.
So what do you make of this relationship with
Pakistan? The Pakistani military intelligence
is involved in creating the Taliban. They've
got to know about the connections with al-Qaeda
and bin Laden. We give them, what, I can't
remember the number, but it's hundreds of
millions of dollars in military support. And
it's much--it's somewhat like the Saudi relationship.
But you have, clearly, a dual game going with
[crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: Absolutely. Absolutely a dual game.
The Pakistanis--that great champion of democracy
and human rights Benazir Bhutto created the
Taliban. And the original reason for creating
the Taliban was to protect Pakistani truck
traffic as it drove across Afghanistan to
deliver goods in Iran.
JAY: 'Cause the country was in chaos.
KIRIAKOU: The country was in utter chaos.
JAY: As a result of President Carter, Zbigniew
Brzezinski, and Ronald Reagan's policy of
sucking Russia into a new Vietnam [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: Correct.
JAY: --destroyed the place.
KIRIAKOU: That's right. It was literally destroyed.
So the Taliban began by protecting the trucks.
Then they began setting up posts in villages
along the truck routes. Then they took over
the villages. Then they took over the regions.
Then they took over the states. And the next
thing you know, they took over the whole country.
JAY: And from what I know--and I was there
and made a film there and spoke to a lot of
Afghans--in the early days, it was quite popular,--
KIRIAKOU: It was.
JAY: --even amongst secular, modern Afghans
in Kabul, because the place was going to shit.
KIRIAKOU: Yes, that's right. And at least
in those early days of the Taliban, people
weren't being killed in shootouts in the street
or having your relatives kidnapped and lynched
because of a property dispute. They really
did bring law and order in those early days
and they did protect Pakistan's truck traffic.
But then everything spun out of control. And
the next thing we know, there's a militant
theocracy in Afghanistan.
I believe that even after things went bad
in Afghanistan with the Taliban, that the
Pakistani government continued to support
them, continued to fund them, and continued
to give them safe haven when they needed it,
which led to no end of problems, including,
probably, the September 11 attacks.
JAY: So you're now head of counterterrorism
for the CIA in Pakistan. You're working with
Pakistani authorities. And how does this work
within Pakistani authorities? Some of them
were off here playing footsie with al-Qaeda
and the Taliban, and the other ones are working
with you.
KIRIAKOU: That's a great question, and the
answer is kind of complicated.
The Pakistani authorities who were assigned
to work with us: almost entirely Army officers.
All had been educated in the U.K., trained
in the U.K. or the U.S., solidly pro-American.
And I can honestly tell you with a completely
straight face that I never asked them for
anything that they didn't give me. Anything
I needed, it was done, and I mean from the
lowliest private all the way up to the brigadier
general who was in charge of the program.
JAY: Well, not everything. You must have asked
them where bin Laden was. They didn't [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: They didn't--they said they didn't
know.
Now, with that said, there were certainly
other very powerful elements of the Pakistani
government, and specifically the Pakistani
military, that were solidly pro-Taliban, in
many cases pro-al-Qaeda, and did not just
nothing to help us, but actively tried to
stop us from making inroads against al-Qaeda.
Even in the Abu Zubaydah operation, we never
told the Pakistanis who we were going after.
We called him Mr. Fish, because we had told
him that he was a big fish.
So the night that we hit--.
JAY: Okay, give us some context. We haven't
told that story yet.
KIRIAKOU: Sure. Just after my arrival in Pakistan,
we got word from headquarters that Abu Zubaydah
was somewhere in the country. And at the time,
we thought Abu Zubaydah was the number-three
in al-Qaeda. That turned out to not be true.
Not only was he not the number-three (Khalid
Sheikh Mohammed was the number-three), but
Abu Zubaydah had never actually joined al-Qaeda.
He created and ran al-Qaeda's two training
camps, but he never pledged fealty to Osama
bin Laden. He was an independent operator.
So we were afraid that the people that we
were dealing with on a daily basis would tell
somebody in their organization who the target
was and that word would get out and Abu Zubaydah
would be tipped off. So we never told them,
until we actually had him in custody, who
it was we had been looking for.
JAY: Where'd the intelligence come from that
he was number three?
KIRIAKOU: Oh, you get bits and pieces from
various human sources. You get liaison sources
reporting to our liaison officers overseas.
You might get some intercepts, press reporting.
You put everything together, and you try to
come up with this structure for al-Qaeda.
And the best information we had in 2002 was
that he was number three.
Don't forget, in February 2002, we didn't
know who Khalid Sheikh Mohammed was. We had
no idea not only that he was a major player
in al-Qaeda, but that he had masterminded
the 9/11 attacks. That's how bad the intelligence
was back then.
JAY: Okay. So you grab this guy. Now, you're
in on organizing the mission to grab this
guy. How does that work?
KIRIAKOU: We had never hit more than two sites
simultaneously before in Pakistan. We would--my
first day on the job, I went into the senior
CIA officer's office and I said, what exactly
do you want me to do here? And he said, I
want you to come up with a modus operandi
for taking down a terrorist safe house; we've
not done that yet. I said, okay.
So I remember sitting at my desk with a legal
pad and a pen and thinking, well, if I was
going to take down a terrorist safe house,
how would I start? Well, I would do it at
2 a.m., because they would most likely be
asleep by 2 a.m. So I wrote 0200 at the top
of the paper. And then I just tried to come
up with this step-by-step plan of how I wanted
to do it.
So, finally I went to him and I said, I think
I've come up with a plan; I'm ready to give
it a try. And he said, well, we've got this
little bit of information that there's this
house. Here's the address. And there might
be an al-Qaeda guy in it. I said, alright,
I'll get a group of guys together, and we're
going to hit it tonight at two, and wish me
luck.
JAY: And you'd never done this before.
KIRIAKOU: I had never done this before in
my life.
JAY: I don't understand this. I would have
imagined the CIA had these specialist--take
down houses specialists, and they fly in,
Jack Bauer shows up.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, that all came later, because
of September 11. But before, I mean, it was
sad sacks like me.
JAY: But CIA's been doing ops for--since they
founded [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: Yeah. But not like this, though.
This was different.
So I came up with a plan. I got a couple of
the guys together. We called our Pakistani
counterparts. And I said, listen, why don't
we meet up at 12? I'm going to brief you on
this operation that I want us to do tonight.
So we did. And I planned it so that we were
about a block away from the house at 1:55
a.m., and then at 1:57 we were going to get
out of the car, and then we were going to
walk to the house. And then, right at 0200--and
we synchronized our watches--we were going
to use a battering ram to break down the door
of the house. The Pakistanis always go in
first--it's their country. We're going to
grab the guy and take him into custody.
So that's what we did. Oh-two-hundred, we
broke down the door with a battering ram,
and we caught this 19-year-old Tunisian kid
who had just escaped across the border from
Afghanistan and found refuge in this house.
So I said, hey, success. Well, let's try it
again in a couple of nights. And the second
time we did it, we caught in Egyptian who
had been a member of Egyptian Islamic Jihad.
He was actually wanted in Egypt, had been
charged with crimes there, and had escaped
to Afghanistan. And I thought, okay, well,
this is pretty good. Once or twice we did
two in a night. We would set up two separate
teams and do it. And almost every time we
did this, we would catch somebody, and they
were almost exclusively low-level nobodies,
usually teenagers. They would just start to
cry. They wouldn't resist in any way.
JAY: What would happen to them?
KIRIAKOU: We would send them, usually, back
to Afghanistan, or in some cases to Guantanamo.
Remember, the whole purpose of Guantanamo
in those early days was just to have some
place to put them until we could figure out
where to put them on trial, if they should
be tried in the U.S. or flown back to their
home countries to be tried there. Guantanamo
was never, ever supposed to be a permanent
place.
JAY: Some of the people you've picked up and
sent to Guantanamo, you didn't know they'd
actually done anything, other than they were
in this house.
KIRIAKOU: Correct. Correct. But my position
back then was, if you're an Arab in Pakistan
with no money, no job, no passport, and no
plausible explanation for what you're doing
there and how you got there, you're al-Qaeda
and you're going to go to Guantanamo until
we can figure out what we are going to do
with you. There were so many people we had
to go after, there was just no time to really
go into things with them, to decide, yes,
this is really who they are, this is why they're
here.
And another thing is many of them, most of
them had been briefed in advance on what to
do and what to say if you're captured. So
everybody told us the same exact story. And
the story was that they had gone to Pakistan
to learn Arabic, they were going to take Arabic
classes, which is odd because nobody speaks
Arabic in Pakistan. They speak Urdu.
JAY: These were mostly Afghans?
KIRIAKOU: They were all Arabs.
JAY: Well, how could they go learn Arabic?
KIRIAKOU: Precisely.
So they flew to Karachi. And they were so
happy to have arrived safely in Karachi that
they decided to take a taxi to the grand mosque
to thank God for their safe delivery.
Well, there is no grand mosque in Karachi.
The grand mosque is in Islamabad.
And they accidentally, doggone it, left their
passports in the taxi, and that's why they
have no passport. And so they didn't know
where to stay, where to live. So they went
to the local Arab coffee shop (there is no
Arab coffee shop in any of these places),
and they met some Arabs there from their own
country, and the Arabs said, oh, not to worry,
I'll put you in this house, and you wait there
until I can get the embassy to replace your
passport.
Okay? So no matter what country they came
from, they all told exactly the same story.
JAY: So these were just, you think, young,
naive recruits that didn't [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: Yeah. They were nobodies. Kids.
JAY: So then you go in and you go after what
you think is the number-three.
KIRIAKOU: It was more complicated than that.
We got this message from headquarters saying
that Abu Zubaydah was in Pakistan and we had
to catch him. But Pakistan's the size of Texas,
and it has the population of California. So
to say, just go catch him, it meant nothing
to me.
So we flew an analyst in from headquarters,
what was then called a targeting analyst,
somebody who isn't thinking the big thoughts
to write an article in the president's daily
brief about, you know, a country's next election,
but somebody who's focused on poring through
raw data to try to locate someone who we have
as a target. And it took him about--I'm going
to say two or three weeks. And finally he
came to me and said, I've narrowed it down,
but only to 14 possible locations. Well, we
had never hit more than two spots before in
a single night, so the prospect of hitting
14 simultaneously was daunting. I cabled headquarters
and I said, I'm going to need help.
JAY: So you go after the guy who's number
three and you get the guy, and this begins
a chain of events which actually winds you
up in jail, really, and you can date that
chain from probably around here, because some
of your colleagues go off to question this
guy. And what happens?
KIRIAKOU: Abu Zubaydah was very severely wounded
when we captured him. A Pakistani policeman
shot him three times with an AK-47 and he
nearly died. In fact, the doctor at the emergency
room where we took him that night told me
that he had never seen wounds so severe where
the patient lived.
So we flew Abu Zubaydah to a nearby military
base. And I sat with him for almost 48 hours.
Actually, it was more than 48 hours. I thought
it was 48 hours, and then in discovery in
my case I learned it was 56 hours. So I just
sat at the foot of his bed.
JAY: Just quickly, when John says, "my case",
he means when the CIA charged him and they
were going through all the back-and-forth
of discoveries that eventually led to his
conviction, and go back to earlier and you'll
find out he was in jail for 23 months and
he's now under house arrest, and we're going
to tell this whole story in the next segment
or two.
KIRIAKOU: Okay. So I sat with him for 56 hours.
He was in a coma for most of that. He drifted
out of it a couple of times. At one point,
he asked me to smother him with a pillow.
He asked me for a glass of red wine, which
I thought was just a delusion.
But then, later on, the next day, he was a
little more aware of what had happened. And
we talked about the 9/11 attacks briefly.
We talked about Christianity and Islam. He
told me that he enjoyed writing poetry. He
cried. He said he would never know the touch
of a woman, he would never know the joy of
fatherhood. And I urged him repeatedly to
cooperate. And he said no, that he wasn't
going to cooperate. He told me at one point,
you seem like a nice guy, but you're the enemy,
and I'll never cooperate with the enemy.
JAY: Did he say why you're the enemy?
KIRIAKOU: Well, I was an American. It was
as simple as that.
He did say that he didn't want to attack the
United States on September 11, that that was
bin Laden's decision. He wanted to attack
Israel. But bin Laden overruled him and said
no, that they were attacking the United States.
JAY: But he never--there was no ambiguity
or qualification from him that 9/11 [incompr.]
KIRIAKOU: Oh, no, no, no. Not at all. Nine/Eleven
was bin Laden, most definitely.
So his wounds, like I say, were so severe
he really needed to be treated, formally treated,
not just patched up. So the CIA sent a private
jet with a trauma surgeon from Johns Hopkins
University medical center. They flew to the
military base. And three FBI agents and I
loaded him onto a gurney and carried him up
onto the plane, we laid him across the luggage
rack at the back, and he took off. He went
to a so-called secret location, and I never
saw him again.
JAY: Now, you heard about the interrogation.
What did you hear?
KIRIAKOU: Yes. I heard--when I got back to
headquarters, I heard that he had been uncooperative,
that he had been subjected to waterboarding
one time, and that he had cracked. And after
he cracked, he gave us actionable intelligence
that saved American lives. That turned out
to be a complete lie. He had not been waterboarded
one time; he had been waterboarded 83 times.
In fact, he was cooperative when he was being
interviewed by the FBI. We know from the FBI
agent who was interviewing him that he was
cooperative. And this FBI agent, Ali Soufan,
had made real inroads in this relationship
with Abu Zubaydah.
What happened then was the president ordered
the FBI out, the CIA in, and the CIA began
torturing him using several different methods
and culminating in waterboarding.
JAY: How do you know it was the president
that ordered it?
KIRIAKOU: Well, that's what came out over
the course of the investigation later on,
that these tactics had all been approved by
the president and that the White House was
unhappy with the pace of the interrogations.
They wanted information more quickly.
See, bin Laden said right after September
11 that he was planning another attack that
would dwarf what happened on September 11.
So, many CIA officers were convinced that
Abu Zubaydah had that information, and they
were determined to get it out of him. That's
why they got rough so quickly.
JAY: There's a lot of discussion in media,
and there was in the political circles and
so on, about torture and the waterboarding
and the Pakistani connection with the Taliban
and all the rest.
KIRIAKOU: Mhm.
JAY: But what do you think of the bigger picture,
the overall policy of allying with essentially
what more or less is a military--close to--has
been a military dictatorship in Pakistan,
and when it's not a straightforward dictatorship,
it's behind-the-scenes military rule just
beneath the sort of political structures,
allying with warlords in Afghanistan, allying
with a dictatorial monarchy in Saudi Arabia,
Qatar, go on and on and on, that in order
to maintain America as the hegemon in the
region, we have to--what I said earlier, you
know, do bad things, supposedly for good reasons,
allied with the worst kind of forces you could
possibly dredge up?
KIRIAKOU: Yes. I think as a country we're
going to have to make a decision at some point,
and that decision's going to have to be whether
we are going to be this beacon of human rights
that we'd like to think we are, this shining
city on a hill that everybody looks up to,
where everybody wants to move, or are we going
to be the biggest, toughest bully on the block,
because we can't be both at the same time.
You know, I happened to be on the State Department's
website the other day, and I clicked on the
link for the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights,
and Labor. And right at the top of their website,
they have a link to the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights. And Article 5 of that declaration
says that no person shall be subjected to
torture or to humiliating treatment. Okay?
This is a joke. Congress mandates the State
Department every single year with producing
a human rights report on every single country
with which we have diplomatic relations.
I was the embassy human rights officer for
two years in Bahrain when I was living there,
and I can tell you that when you go in to
a host government's foreign ministry and you
dress them down for disrespecting human rights,
but then you have a CIA officer going to see
his counterpart in the afternoon and telling
him, telling the foreign intelligence counterpart,
we want you to take this prisoner and we want
you to really lean on him, but just be sure
to give us a transcript of what he says, you
completely undercut your entire policy.
So, while we have these laws that are supposed
to protect human rights and supposed to mandate
the protection of human rights overseas, it's
really little more than a bad joke, because
we don't respect human rights. I mean, we
had, under George W. Bush, our own Justice
Department doing back flips to try to figure
out how to legally justify torture. And they
contorted themselves in such a way that they
did endorse torture. And we go through life
saying, okay, well, then, if the Justice Department
said it's right, then it must be right, so
we can go ahead and torture. It makes no sense.
JAY: It's been nonstop since World War II.
KIRIAKOU: It's been nonstop since World War
II.
You know, I'll tell you another thing. In
the course of my research since I've left
the agency, I've found a picture that ran
on the front page of The Washington Post in
1968, and it was a picture of an American
soldier waterboarding a North Vietnamese prisoner.
When that picture was published, the Pentagon
began an investigation, they court-martialed
the soldier, they charged him with torture,
they convicted him, and they jailed him. So
why was torture wrong in 1968, but then it's
right in 2002 and it's right in 2015 and nobody's
prosecuted for committing torture? It's the
ultimate in hypocrisy to me.
JAY: Alright. Thanks for joining us.
KIRIAKOU: Thanks for having me.
JAY: We're going to continue our series of
interviews with John Kiriakou on Reality Asserts
Itself on The Real News Network.